COLIN" Mary took the picture back to the house when she went to her supper and
she showed it to Martha he said Martha with great pride. "I never knew our Dickon
was as clever as that. That there's a picture of a missile thrush on her nest,
as large as life and twice as natural." Then Mary knew Dickon had meant
the picture to be a message. He had meant that she might be sure he would keep her
secret. Her garden was her nest and she was like a missile
thrush. Oh, how she did like that queer, common boy! She hoped he would come back
the very next day and she fell asleep looking forward to the
morning. But you never know what the weather will do in York particularly in the
springtime. She was awakened in the night by the sound of rain beating with heavy
drops against her window. It was pouring down in torrents and the wind was Bing
around the corners and in the chimneys of the huge old house. Mary sat up in bed
and felt miserable and angry. "The rain is as contrary as I ever
was," she said. "It came because it knew I did not want it." She threw herself back
on her pillow and buried her face. She did not cry, but she lay and hated the
sound of the heavily beating rain, she hated the wind and its
weing She could could not go to sleep again. The mournful sound kept her awake
because she felt mournful herself. If she had felt happy it would
probably have lulled her to sleep. How it wed and how the big raindrops poured
down and beat against the pain It sounds just like a person lost
on the mo and wandering on and on crying," she said. She had been lying awake turning
from side to side for about an hour, when suddenly something made her sit up in
bed and turn her head toward the door listening. She listened and she
listened. "It isn't the wind now," she said in a loud whisper. "That isn't the wind. It
is different. It is that crying I heard before." The door of her room was a jar
and the sound came down the corridor, a far off faint sound of fretful
crying. She listened for a few minutes and each minute she became more and more
sure. She felt as if she must find out what it was. It seemed even stranger than
the secret garden and the buried key. Perhaps the fact that she was in a
rebellious mood made her bold. She put her foot out of bed and stood on the
floor. "I am going to find out what it is,"
she said. "Everybody is in bed and I don't care about Mrs. Medlock I I don't
care!" There was a candle by her bedside and she took it up and went softly out
of the room. The corridor looked very long and dark, but she was too excited to
mind that. She thought she remembered the corners she must turn to find the short
corridor with the door covered with tapestry— —the one Mrs. Medlock had come
through the day she lost herself. The sound had come up that passage.
So she went on with her dim light, almost feeling her way, her heart beating so
loud that she fancied she could hear it.
The far off faint crying went on and led her. Sometimes it stopped for a moment or
so and then began again. Was this the right corner to turn? She stopped and thought. Yes it
was. Down this passage and then to the left, and then up two broad steps, and
then then to the right again. Yes, there was the tapestry door. She pushed it open
very gently and closed it behind her, and she stood in the corridor and could hear
the crying quite plainly, though it was not loud. It was on the other side of the
wall at her left and a few yards further on there was a door. She could see a
glimmer of light coming from beneath it.
The Someone was crying in that room, and it was quite a young Someone. So she
walked to the door and pushed it open, and there she was standing in the
room! It was a big room with ancient, handsome furniture in it. There was a low
fire glowing faintly on the hearth and a nightlight burning by the side of a
carved for posted bed hung with brickade and on the bed was lying a boy, crying
fretfully. Mary wondered if she was in a real place or if she had fallen asleep
again and was dreaming without knowing it. The boy had a sharp, delicate face the
color of ivory and he seemed to have
eyes too big for it. He had also a lot of hair which tumbled over his forehead in
heavy locks and made his thin face seem smaller. He looked like a boy who had
been ill, but he was crying more as if he
were tired and cross than as if he were in pain. Mary stood near the door with
her candle in her hand, holding her breath. Then she crept across the room,
and as she drew nearer the light attracted the boy's attention and he
turned his head on his pillow and stared at her, his gray eyes opening so wide
that they seemed immense. "'WHO ARE YOU he said at last in a half frightened
whisper. "Are you a ghost?" "No, I am not," Mary answered, her own whisper sounding half
frightened.
"Are you one?" He stared and stared and stared. Mary could not help noticing what strange
eyes he had. They were agate gray and they looked too big for his face because
they had black lashes all around them. "No," he replied after waiting a moment or so.
"I am Colin." "Who is Colin?" she faltered. "I am Colin Craven. Who are you?" "I am Mary
Lennox Mr Mr. Craven is my uncle." "He is my father," said the boy. "Your father!" gasped
Mary. "No one ever told me he had a boy!
Why didn't they?" "Come here," he said, still keeping his strange eyes fixed on her with an
anxious expression. She came close to the bed and he put out his hand and touched
her. "You are real, aren't you?" he said. "I have such real dreams very often. You
might be one of them." Mary had slipped on a woolen wrapper before she left her
room and she put a piece of it between his fingers. "Rub that and see how thick and
warm it is," she said. "I will pinch you a
little if you like, to show you how real
I am. For a minute I thought you might be
a dream too." "Where did you come from?" he
asked. "From my own room. The wind wed so I couldn't go to sleep and I heard someone
crying and wanted to find out who it was.
What were you crying for?" "Because I couldn't go to sleep
either and my head achd Tell me your name again." "Mary Lennox. Did no one ever
tell you I had come to live here?" He was still fingering the fold of her rapper
but he began to look a little more as if he believed in her
reality. "No," he answered. "They dared Why?" asked Mary. "Because I should
have been afraid you would see me. I won't let people see me and talk me
over." "Why?" Mary asked again, feeling more mystified every moment. "Because I am like
this always, ill and having to lie down.
My father won't let people talk me over either. The servants are not allowed to
speak about me. If I live I may be a hunchback, but I Shan live. My father
hates to think I may be like him." "Oh, what
a queer house this is!" Mary said. "What a queer house! Everything is a kind of
secret. Rooms are locked up and gardens are locked up— —and you! Have you been
locked up?" "No. I stay in this room because
I don't want to be moved out of it. It tires me too
much." "Does your father come and see you?"
Mary ventured. "Sometimes. Generally when I'm asleep. He doesn't want to see
me." "Why?" Mary could not help asking again.
A sort of angry shadow passed over the boy's face. "My mother died when I was born and
it makes him wretched to look at me. He thinks I don't know, but I've heard
people talking. He almost hates me." "He hates the garden, because she died," said
Mary half speaking to herself. "What garden?" the boy asked. "Oh! just— —just a
garden she used to like," Mary stammered.
"Have you been here always?"
"Nearly always. Sometimes I have been taken to places at the seaside, but I
won't stay because people stare at me. I used to wear an iron thing to keep my
back straight, but a grand doctor came from London to see me and said it was
stupid. He told them to take it off and keep me out in the fresh air. I hate
fresh air and I don't want to go out." "I didn't when first I came here," said Mary.
"Why do you keep looking at me like that?"
"Because of the dreams that are so real," he answered rather
fretfully. "Sometimes when I open my eyes I don't believe I'm
awake." "We're both awake," said Mary. She glanced around the room with its high
ceiling and shadowy corners and dim Fire Light It looks quite like a dream, and
it's the middle of the night, and everybody in the house is asleep— —everybody but us.
We are wide awake." "I don't want it to be a dream," the boy said
restlessly. Mary thought of something all at once. "If you don't like people to see
you," she began, "do you want me to go away?" He still held the fold of her
wrapper and he gave it a little pull. "No," he said. "I should be sure you were a
dream if you went. If you are real, sit down on that big foot stol and talk. I
want to hear about you." Mary put down her candle on the table near the bed and sat
down on the cushioned stool. She did not want to go away at all.
She wanted to stay in the mysterious hidden away room and talk to the mysterious
boy. "What do you want me to tell you?" she
said. He wanted to know how long she had been at mistle he wanted to know which corridor
her room was on; he wanted to know what she had been doing; if she disliked the
more as he disliked it; where she had lived before she came to Yorkshire. She answered all these
questions and many more and he lay back on his pillow and
listened. He made her tell him a great deal about India and about her voyage across the
ocean. She found out that because he had been an invalid he had not learned
things as other children had. One of his nurses had taught him to read when he
was quite little and he was always reading and looking at pictures in splendid
books. Though his father rarely saw him when he was awake, he was given all sorts
of wonderful things to amuse himself with. He never seemed to have been amused,
however. He could have anything he asked for and was never made to do anything he
did not like to do everyone is obliged to do what pleases me," he said indifferently. "It
makes me ill to be angry. No one believes I shall live to grow
up." He said it as if he was so accustomed
to the idea that it had ceased to matter to him at
all. He seemed to like the sound of Mary's voice. As she went on talking he
listened in a drowsy, interested way. Once or twice she wondered if he were not
gradually falling into a doze. But at last he asked a question which opened up a new
subject. "How old are you?" he asked. "I am 10 answered Mary, forgetting herself for the
moment, "and so are you." "How do you know that?" he demanded in
a surprised voice. "Because when you were born the garden door was locked and the
key was buried. And it has been locked for 10 years." Colin half sat up, turning toward
her, leaning on his elbows. "What garden door was locked? Who
did it? Where was the key buried?" he exclaimed as if he were suddenly very much
interested. "It— —it was the garden Mr.
Craven hates," said Mary nervously. "He locked the door. No one— —no
one knew where he buried the key."
"What sort of a garden is it?" Colin persisted eagerly. "No one has been
allowed to go into it for 10 years," was Mary's careful
answer. But it was too late to be careful.
He was too much like herself. He too had had nothing to think
about and the idea of a hidden garden attracted him as it had attracted her. He
asked question after question. Where was it? Had she never looked for the door?
Had she never asked the gardeners? "They won't talk about it," said
Mary. "I think they have been told not to answer questions." "I would make them," said
Colin. "Could you?" Mary faltered, beginning to feel frightened. If he could make
people answer questions, who knew what might happen everyone is obliged to please me.
I told you that," he said. "If I were to live, this place would sometime belong to
me. They all know that. I would make them tell me." Mary had not known that she
herself had been spoiled, but she could see quite plainly that this mysterious boy had
been. He thought that the whole world belonged to him. How peculiar he was and
how coolly he spoke of not living. "Do you think you won't live?" she
asked, partly because she was curious and partly in hope of making him forget the
garden. "I don't suppose I shall," he answered as indifferently as he had spoken
before. "Ever since I remember anything I have heard people say I Shan At first
they thought I was too little to understand and now they think I don't
hear. But I do. My doctor is my father's
cousin. He is quite poor and if I die he will have all mistle when my father is
dead. I should think he wouldn't want me to live."
"Do you want to live?" inquired Mary. "No," he answered, in a cross, tired fashion. "But I
don't want to die. When I feel ill I lie
here and think about it until I cry and cry." "I have heard you crying three times,"
Mary said, "but I did not know who it was.
Were you crying about that?" She did so want him to forget the garden. "I dare say,"
he answered. "Let us talk about something else. Talk about that garden. Don't you want to see
it?" "Yes," answered Mary, in quite a low voice. "I do," he went on
persistently. "I don't think I ever really wanted to see anything before, but I want
to see that garden. I want the key dug up.
I want the door unlocked. I would let them take me there in my chair. That
would be getting fresh air. I am going to make them open the
door." He had become quite excited and his strange eyes began to shine like stars
and looked more immense than ever. "They have to please me," he said. "I will make
them take me there and I will let you go, too." Mary's hands clutched each other.
Everything would be spoiled— —everything!
Dickon would never come back. She would never again feel like a missile thrush
with a safe hidden nest. "Oh, don't— —don't— —don't— —don't do that!" she cried out. He
stared as if he thought she had gone crazy! "Why?" he exclaimed. "You said you
wanted to see it." "I do," she answered almost with a sob in her throat, "but if
you make them open the door and take you in like that it will never be a secret
again." He leaned still farther forward. "A secret," he said. "What do you mean? Tell
me." Mary's words almost tumbled over one another. "You see— —you see," she panted, "if no
one knows but ourselves— —if there was a door, hidden somewhere under the ivy— —if
there was— —and we could find it; and if we could slip through it together and shut
it behind us, and no one knew anyone was inside and we called it our garden and pretended
that— —that we were missile thrushes and it was our nest, and if we played there
almost every day and dug and planted seeds and made it all come alive—" "Is it
dead?" he interrupted her. "It soon will be if no one cares for it," she went on. "The
bulbs will live but the roses—" He stopped her again as excited as she was
herself. "What a bulbs?" he put in quickly.
"They are daffodils and lies and snow drops They are working in the earth now—
—pushing up pale green points because the spring is coming." "Is the spring coming?" he
said. "What is it like? You don't see it in
rooms if you are ill." "It is the sun shining on the rain and the rain falling
on the sunshine, and things pushing up and working under the earth," said Mary. "If
the garden was a secret and we could get into it we could watch the things grow
bigger every day, and see how many roses are alive. Don't you
see? Oh, don't you see how much nicer it would be if it was a
secret?" He dropped back on his pillow and lay there with an odd expression on his
face. "I never had a secret," he said, "except that one about not living to grow up.
They don't know I know that, so it is a sort of secret. But I like this kind
better." "If you won't make them take you to the garden," pleaded Mary,
"perhaps— —I feel almost sure I can find out how to get in sometime. And then— —if
the doctor wants you to go out in your chair, and if you can always do what you
want to do, perhaps— —perhaps we might find some boy who would push you, and we could
go alone and it would always be a secret garden." "I should— —like—
—that," he said very slowly, his eyes looking dreamy. "I should like that. I should not
mind fresh air in a secret garden." Mary began to recover her breath and feel
safer because the idea of keeping the secret seemed to please him. She felt
almost sure that if she kept on talking and could make him see the garden in his
mind as she had seen it he would like it
so much that he could not bear to think that everybody might into it when they
chose. "I'll tell you what I think it would be like, if we could go into it," she
said. "It has been shut up so long things have grown into a tangle
perhaps." He lay quite still and listened while she went on talking about the
roses which might have clambered from tree to tree and hung down— —about the
many birds which might have built their nests there because it was so safe.
And then she told him about the robin and Ben Weatherstaff, and there was so
much to tell about the robin and it was so easy and safe to talk about it that
she ceased to feel afraid. The robin pleased him so much that he smiled until he looked almost
beautiful, and at first Mary had thought that he was even plainer than herself,
with his big eyes and heavy locks of hair. "I did not know birds could be like
that," he said. "But if you stay in a room you never see things. What a lot of
things you know. I feel as if you had been inside that
garden." She did not know what to say, so she did not say
anything. He evidently did not expect an answer and the next moment he gave her a
surprise. "I am going to let you look at something," he said. "Do you see that
rose-colored silk curtain hanging on the wall over the mantle piece
Mary had not noticed it before, but she looked up and saw it. It was a curtain of
soft silk hanging over what seemed to be some picture. "Yes," she answered. "There is a cord
hanging from it," said Colin. "Go and pull it." Mary got up, much mystified, and found
the cord. When she pulled it the silk curtain ran back on rings and when it
ran back it uncovered a picture.
It was the picture of a girl with a laughing
face. She had bright hair tied up with a blue ribbon and her gay, lovely eyes were
exactly like Colin's unhappy ones agot gray and looking twice as big as they
really were because of the black lashes all around them. "She is my mother," said
Colin complainingly. "I don't see why she died. Sometimes I hate her for doing it."
"How queer!" said Mary.
"If she had lived I believe I should not have been ill always," he grumbled. "I dare
say I should have Liv too. And my father would not have hated to look at me. I
dare say I should have had a strong back.
Draw the curtain again." Mary did as she was told and returned to her foot stol
She is much prettier than you," she said, "but her eyes are just like yours— —at
least they are the same shape and color.
Why is the curtain drawn over her?" He moved uncomfortably. "I made them do it," he
said. "Sometimes I don't like to see her looking at me. She smiles too much when I
am ill and miserable. Besides, she is mine and I don't want everyone to see
her." There were a few moments of silence and then Mary
spoke. "What would Mrs. Medlock do if she found out that I had been here?" she
inquired. "She would do as I told her to do," he
answered. "And I should tell her that I wanted you to come here and talk to me
every day. I am glad you came." "So am I,"
said Mary. "I will come as often as I can, but"— "—she hesitated—" —"I shall have to look
every day for the garden door." "Yes, you must," said Colin, "and you can tell me about it
afterwards He lay thinking a few minutes, as he had done before, and then he spoke
again. "I think you shall be a secret, too," he said. "I will not tell them until they
find out. I can always send the nurse out
of the room and say that I want to be by myself. Do you know
Martha?" "Yes, I know her very well," said Mary. "She waits on me." He nodded his head
toward W the outer corridor. "She is the one who is asleep in the other
room. The nurse went away yesterday to stay all night with her sister and she
always makes Martha attend to me when she wants to go out. Martha shall tell
you when to come here." Then Mary understood Martha's troubled look when she had asked
questions about the crying. "Martha knew about you all the
time?" she said. "Yes; she off often attends to me. The nurse likes to get away from
me and then Martha comes." "I have been here a long time," said
Mary. "Shall I go away now? Your eyes look sleepy." "I wish I could go to sleep before
you leave me," he said rather shyly. "Shut your eyes," said Mary, drawing her foot
stool closer, "and I will do what my Aya
used to do in India. I will pat your hand stroke it and sing something quite
low." "I should like that perhaps," he said drowsily. Somehow she was sorry for him
and did not want him to lie awake, so she leaned against the bed and began to
stroke and pat his hand and sing a very low little chanting song in
Hindustani. "That is nice," he said more drowsily still, and she went on chanting and
stroking, but when she looked at him again his black lashes were lying close
against his cheeks, for his eyes were shut and he was fast
asleep. So she got up softly, took her candle and crept away without making a